whether you're watching on YouTube or
listening as a podcast remember to
subscribe and hit the bell to track
upcoming releases
written on the 15th of March 2020 this
is the short essay titled situational
assessment right now by Jordan Hall
the story of the unfolding metal
Isis that we have been watching for the
last decade has become enormous ly more
salient over the past few weeks this is
a moment of major risk along many
different fronts it is also a moment of
singular opportunity foremost among them
is to learn the deep code hypothesis has
been that the dynamic attractor of our
current civilization the set of
institutions structures ideas habits and
feedback loops that keep things hanging
together is in the process of
evaporation like a tornado that is
turning back into wind at the same time
a new dynamic attractor is in the
process of formation we are in the
middle of a great transition from one
attractor to another meta systemic
dynamics like the 2008 financial crisis
and it's child the European debt crisis
brexit the 2016 election and the present
covered nineteen crisis are all examples
of and symptoms of that transition we
may or may not manage to navigate the
journey but the journey is underway
nonetheless the present crisis is
significant it is also only an example
of more to come
we need to navigate this one and learn
how to become exquisite at navigating
this entire class of events major threat
vectors let's begin by looking at what
are some of the major threat vectors in
the unfolding meta crisis right now this
is useful both for focusing attention on
points of high risk as well as for
getting a better sense of our message
systemic dynamics implicate and
intensify risks across systems note in
particular how all of the below feedback
on each other medical system overwhelm
when the number of patients needing beds
exceeds the number of beds ventilators
doctors etc all harm metrics shift
significantly to the worse and you get
spillover effects into everything else
that the medical system is otherwise
managing eg car wreck victims don't have
a R or ICU estimated time of arrival
this threat is happening now and is
expanding quickly in both breath number
of locations worldwide and intensity
note that this risk occurs at
hierarchical levels of organization one
Hospital might be overwhelmed but the
city it is in might not Wuhan was
overwhelmed but China as a whole was not
northern Italy was overwhelmed but at
least as of this writing the EU was not
this allows portable resources to flow
from the larger context into areas of
local overwhelm if we cross the point of
global medical overwhelm that will be a
worrying development resource depletion
panic buying resource allocation issues
combined with shut down supply chains
quarantine can lead to real or perceived
threat eg lack of food this can lead to
crime escalating to civic unrest and
beyond eta two weeks if supply chain /
access disruption continues past three
weeks this threat begins to move into
the red cash depletion 70% of the u.s.
population lives paycheck to paycheck
many will see income drop over the next
few days in many cases to zero
particularly in any sort of quarantine
environment if the disruption lasts for
weeks and certainly by six weeks you
will have tens of millions of people who
can't get access to resources even if
the resources are otherwise available
special note different resources are
different rent and mortgage are subtle
and important likely requiring different
approaches and food power water and
Internet as well this cascades both into
civil unrest and into deeper longer-term
economic harm note civil unrest here
does not necessarily mean looting our
well organized rent / mortgage strike is
a perfectly plausible and possibly
necessary event this will move cash -
pshhhh and risk into financial system
risk be careful unless the Cure is also
the poison supply chain overwhelm a mix
of these systemic dynamics put pressure
on supply chains the medical risk for
example could weaken
sensitive areas either directly or
indirectly grocery chains closing to
protect their workers might exacerbate
resource depletion issues as wood truck
drivers getting sick or choosing to
socially distance this threat area
includes physical infrastructure ie
utilities normal disruptions of service
might take longer to repair and
potentially much larger than normal use
of services might overwhelm
infrastructure Civic infrastructure
overwhelm reduction in capacity of
Police EMS fire leads to increasing gaps
in civic infrastructure more narrowly
prisons and the homeless are two major
areas of concern as affected populations
as vectors and as systemic risk
accelerators I'm currently not aware of
any coherent proposals to these two
areas of risk pylon and copycat events
anyone who's been thinking about
dropping an asymmetric attack
particularly by a warfare and cyber
warfare might see this as a high
leverage moment nature hitting us with
another crisis flood fire etc is part of
this threat category continuity of
governance Iran has seen this the
relative balkanization and immaturity of
the leadership system in the West who
have for the past decade preferred to
squabble in inter elite competition and
virtue signaling means that even small
numbers of specific people getting sick
could significantly reduce already
contingent sense / choice making as the
precarious balance of coordination
devolves into power grabs financial
system collapse 2008 to 2015 were never
really healed and the global financial
system is enormous ly fragile the real
economic effects of both the virus and
the cure eg quarantine could push a
number of fragile financial systems into
collapse potentially triggering a
systemic collapse globally breakdown of
global coordination capability since
2008 likely leads to substantially less
effective collective response
potential downward spiral
authoritarianism it is quite likely that
a very significant and novel to our
experience level of authoritarianism
will be requested in brackets required
to address the many different aspects of
the meta-crisis enforce quarantine is
one obvious example this creates a
threat of both intentional slash
strategic bad bi and unintentional
systemic transition into a significant
permanent increase in authoritarianism
at the political level across many
different dimensions as we have seen
with 911 a Patriot Act these things have
a habit of becoming habit multipolar
traps political if cultural 2.0
continues unabated amidst the
meta-crisis a number of downward spirals
can ensue for example a viral
containment strategy that involves
shutting down elections could easily be
read as a politically motivated move and
lead to a civil disobedience reaction
this in turn could justify in quotation
marks harder authoritarian means to
enforce quarantine multipolar traps
geopolitical crisis creates opportunity
gold players everywhere are looking to
see how much of the board they can turn
their color through primary risks one
ordinary geopolitical strategic
maneuvering might exacerbate or
overwhelm systems in any slash
all-of-the-above dynamics tune
geopolitical maneuvering might escalate
out of control the Saudi Russia squabble
that led to the oil crash might be seen
as an example that certainly didn't
reduce the burden on the global
financial system super fragility hole a
crucial insight is that the operating
logic of our current civilization has
been to trade resilience for efficiency
creating fragility from childcare family
education and mental health to supply
chains for food water materiel and
medicine watch out for depletion of
psych meds
we've been optimizing everything to
their limits for half a century this
generates short-term profits and
long-term risk the current situation is
pushing on effectively all systems many
of the vital systems of our civilization
are at or near critical points and as
the meta crisis unfolds small brackets
ordinary the perturbations could break
some or many of these fragile systems
for example while it might seem
relatively trivial right now large-scale
school closures and a massive shift at
telework will not be without durable and
in many ways surprising consequence to
opportunity learning as mentioned at the
top this event provides a uniquely rich
and salient opportunity for learning we
are all of us right now faced with
making meaningful choices in the context
of uncertainty did you buy food two
weeks ago well for the good or bad the
real situation has changed for millions
of store shelves choices have real
consequences moreover many of us are
making choices in the context of
competing ideological worldviews is it
just the flu we are about to find out in
a very real way finally and we are now
faced with increasingly intense
consequences under growing complexity
and the dawning reality that the
governance structures see blue church
that have been making our choices for us
the past 70 years are not well designed
to address these kinds of problems so
what do we get to slash need to learn
systemic fragility trading fragility for
efficiency is a bad trade it works great
in the short term I will always collect
in the end we need to learn this lesson
to the level that creates durable
cultural habits like saying bless you
when someone sneezes it is possible to
have both abundance and antifragility
hopefully this year we will begin to
learn how to get there decentralized
sense-making
many John rabe foremost among them have
noticed
networks have done a vastly better job
of making sense of the unfolding meta
crisis than official channels eg the
mainstream media this isn't surprising
those legacy channels simply won't cut
out for this kind of event out there
best and they are very far from their
best the days of the blue church are in
the rearview at the same time we are
still in the early adolescence of
decentralized sense making there is an
enormous potential here waiting to be
realized
decentralized agency our legacy
institutions are for the most part doing
their level best to serve us and in many
cases they are succeeding but as we saw
in 2008 both the wisdom and integrity of
their choices can often leave much room
for improvement the current crisis is
much more complex and is unfolding
quickly we have now both an opportunity
and plausibly necessity to upgrade our
collective decentralized agency and to
solve problems together the scope of our
decentralized agentic capacity is
enormous remember at the base all agency
is grounded in individual people making
their own choices the more we learn how
to quickly use our capacity for
communicating with nearly anyone in the
world in multiple modalities texts
audio/video symmetric asymmetric to
orient our attention to the right
information people and projects and then
to support coordinated action the more
we can move that agency from the old
twentieth-century hierarchical
bureaucracies I currently run the world
to much more flexible adaptive nuanced
and intelligent 21st century
self-organizing Collective intelligences
in brackets SOC I that can fully respond
to meta systemic dynamics how do we do
this theory first in some sense the path
forward is surprisingly simple six steps
one
upgrade your sovereignty increase your
ability to make effective choices under
a larger diversity and intensity of
contexts there is a lot of room between
panic and denial in the future everyone
counts and has to be able to take
responsibility to upgrade your
discernment increase your ability to
separate signal from noise in particular
the noise of your own biases and
projections learn to deal with reality
before reality deals with you 3 upgrade
your integrity the following is a quote
from Yasuo ko Kimura the Japanese word
toku ter in Chinese which is usually
translated as virtue also means power or
integrity
toku is the consciousness of the whole
that makes your life coherent consistent
and integral therefore toku is integrity
and toku is also power because through
toku your vision action and result
become coherent and consistent success
in life and business requires power to
make your vision realized through action
success thus requires integrity in the
sense of toku the English term integrity
is defined on three levels one being
true to your principles to being true to
your word or commitment and 3 being true
to yourself integrity means being true
to your principle your word and yourself
and total integrity involves a total
Accord between these three levels of
being true
men and women of integrity who have the
powers who sustain their commitment
through to the end and achieve their
objectives sometimes against all odds
are those in whom their principle
commitment and self are all in accord
for we can sustain our commitment only
when it is one that is in accord with
our authentic self and with our deepest
values and principles and quote for
subject to your own integrity support
others in their sovereignty discernment
and integrity five orient your own and
others attention to those who have shown
to your discernment the most sovereignty
discernment and integrity and the most
capacity in supporting others there in
six build individual and collective
skillfulness in all of these things
note that this definitely includes
building physical infrastructure like
communications platforms new economic
models etc but the infrastructure must
always follow and support human capacity
and can never replace an or inhibit
human development wisdom must precede
power from theory it's a practice
practical real-time solutions are being
worked on by tens of thousands of people
right now first order is to try and
point the right people to the right
problems then to point the right people
to the right developing solutions then
to orient everyone to the resources they
need examples include German folk calm
and the coronavirus tech handbook good
solid projects that are entirely self
organized and providing significant
value but there are also people like dr.
I need to go ill whose team at nano bio
sim have highly innovative Science and
Technology ready to bring to the crisis
their gene radar Diagnostics could
potentially change the game for c19 and
all other future viruses does this kind
of potential find its way to the front
via legacy institutions or emergent
institutions come to the fore to save
the day or do we drop the ball
altogether time will tell this is a
moment of significant risk
and opportunity these are just a few of
the projects that I am personally aware
of there are many others and will be
many more on a daily basis I'll update
this document as more structure emerges
to share
whether you're watching on YouTube or
listening as a podcast remember to
subscribe and hit the bell to track
upcoming releases